I've been extremely skeptical about NAD
in the past, or I suppose more
specifically NAD supplements, and I'll
touch on that in a bit later. But
there's this major study that several
people in the community have asked me to
cover. And initially, I wasn't that
excited because, well, I'm a little
burnt out from the NAD angle. But after
reading the study, there may be some
hope that NAD could really play a role
in this case against Alzheimer's
disease. So, let me explain the
highlights and then I'd like to show you
an incredibly unlikely supplement and
possibly a nutrition style that has
evidence behind it not only improving
NAD in the brain, but combating
Alzheimer's disease. This is going to be
so cool. This major study that
everyone's been sending me to discuss
tried to figure out if we raise NAD
levels in the brain, does that impact
Alzheimer's disease progression? So if
we rewind a bit for context, you might
be interested to know that Alzheimer's
disease brain has a reduced
concentration of NAD molecules relative
to NADH molecules. This is data
collected from human Alzheimer's
diseased brain samples. The AD there, if
it wasn't obvious, is Alzheimer's
disease. So we know that there's either
less of the NAD or more of the NADH
molecules creating a lower ratio. This
is seen as a bad thing. But why is that?
Well, NAD is known to be involved in
hundreds of enzyatic reactions within
your cells. Specifically, it's involved
in DNA repair, glucose metabolism,
neurogenesis. That's a fancy term for
more brain cells to form. And synaptic
plasticity, a fancy way of saying that
you're greater connections between your
brain cells, which is a good thing to
have considering that you want your
brain cells to communicate effectively.
And that's just a small list of the ways
that NAD impacts your brain cells
health. So you can imagine that a low
brain level of NAD leads to more DNA
damage, less metabolism function, less
brain adaptability and well other stuff
like that. So now that we know that NAD
to NADH ratio is low in Alzheimer's
disease, what might happen if we I don't
know pump it up? That's what this study
that we're focusing on did in this
section in animals, but we'll be
returning to humans soon. Here we're
looking at images of brain cells and the
green fluoresence there is a literal
measure of DNA damage. So the more green
that you see in the images the worse.
It's also quantified on the graph on the
right. The FAD condition there is the
Alzheimer's disease condition. So as
expected with lower brain NAD there's
also more DNA damage. But here's the
first sign of good news. That far right
condition is when the same Alzheimer's
disease condition is supplied with
additional NAD and lo and behold there
is a normalization of the DNA damage.
Now technically this is a
neuroprotective compound that boosts NAD
but it isn't a direct injection of NAD
and we'll return to that in a bit. The
point here and I can conf confirm that
it's also true for multiple other
measures of brain cell health is that
NAD boosting reverses many of the
different internal problems of the brain
cells and what they experience. So DNA
damage, neurogenesis, recovery and so
on. Still, and this is important to
note, outside the context of this study,
we shouldn't ever just look at the
cellular experiments and assume that
leads to improvements in actual
day-to-day living with Alzheimer's
disease. So, keeping that in mind, we
should actually look at the functional
outcomes, the functional measurements
like improvements in learning, memory,
and the like. Fortunately, we have
plenty of access to that kind of work on
measures of memory. The lower bars are,
the worse the memory function. The
lowest bar there is the Alzheimer's
disease condition. Clearly, they're not
doing so hot. However, incredibly
encouragingly, boosting NAD led to a
recovery of the memory function back to
normal non Alzheimer's levels. To be
crystal clear here, we're talking about
complete reversal of Alzheimer's disease
with NAD boosting in this model. Okay,
now we're talking. So, all we have to do
is boost our brain NAD and we're back in
business. Alzheimer's banish to the
depths of the netherworld. For that, the
obvious would be to use what was used in
this study.
But it's an injection and it's not
available yet. Definitely a shame, but
there are alternatives and they don't
require staring down the barrel of a
tiny needle. For example, NAD boosting
supplements like nicotinomide,
nicotenomide monucleotide, nicoti
nicotinomide ribocide uh are all
precursor molecules that are converted
into NAD and have become quite popular.
Now, real quick, why not NAD directly?
It's highly unstable and doesn't
generally translate to effect. So, we
use more stable precursor molecules.
Anyway, like I alluded to at the very
beginning, I've done a lot of analysis
on NAD in the past, and the research has
been extremely weak when it comes to
human research. However, one critique
that I also had in defense of NAD
supplements, was that most NAD studies,
I'm talking about the precursor
molecules, are looking at measures like
triglycerides, LDL, glucose, and things
of that nature. The problem is these
outcomes aren't exactly what NAD was
designed to do mechanistically. However,
now we have significant mechanistic
evidence that NAD boosting reverses
Alzheimer's disease. So, we can focus
our attention on human studies that use
these precursor molecules to investigate
the effect on Alzheimer's disease.
Now, we are incredibly fortunate that
there are such studies and not just one
but at least three. Now, you may have
noticed that the subtitle or section
title for this section of the video is
called The Empire Strikes Back. This is
the point of the trilogy after a new
hope, i.e. NAD, gets a massive kick in
the rear end. In the movies, the I
shouldn't even have to tell you which
movies I'm referencing. The rebels get
their rear ends kicked in the battle of
Hoth. So, what shall be the equivalent
in the world of NAD and Alzheimer's?
Well, it turns out that all three of
these NAD boosting clinical trials show
no effect against Alzheimer's, if that's
a reversal or even a slowing of
Alzheimer's disease. So, as Darth Vader
said to the admiral,
>> "You have failed me for the last time,
NAD booster."
>> Before he crushed his windpipe, we may
have to move off the idea of NAD
boosting through precursor molecules
again. Are we then doomed to a life of
angst trying to fight the empire, i.e.
Alzheimer's disease, forever? Actually,
no. because I was curious if anything
else could boost NAD levels,
particularly in the brain. And I was
pleasantly surprised to find some human
evidence in yet another supplement, one
that might surprise you, which is why
this next section is going to be called
a version of Return of the Jedi. Before
we do get to our savior, I glossed over
the Alzheimer's disease studies, but
there's several interesting aspects
about them that I'm going to get into,
like the changes in brain blood flow and
something called the nodal stress
hypothesis related to NAD boosting and
even in the next supplement like how to
use it more effectively or if genetics
play a role and more. That's all to be
included in the full video of the one
that you're currently watching, which is
included with my Physionic Insider
membership, my research platform, which
comes with all of these perks, too. And
I don't have my new AI system up here
yet, or my master supplement guide that
I just released. All of that is included
as a Physionic Insider. The value just
keeps climbing because I keep putting
tons of time and effort into improving
the insiders. You want to join the
physionic insiders using the link in the
description. I'll speak with you over
there. Now, Luke, the return of the Jedi
is
ketosis.
Well, more specifically, the
supplementation of mediumchain
triglycerides or MCTs. Now, I know it's
kind of out of left field, but hear me
out. I was pleasantly surprised to find
out that there are studies where human
people, not to be confused with
non-human people, are given MCTs and
then there, and this is important, brain
NAD levels of NAD to NADH ratio is
measured. Usually studies measure blood
and then assume the NAD levels are
increased. But we're getting human brain
measurements of NAD here. This is before
and after the NAD ratio increases which
is exactly what we showed here was
diminished in Alzheimer's disease. So
now we have proof that consuming MCTs
raises NAD levels in the brain. Now
granted this is a very shortterm
experiment only lasting a few hours but
guess what? Luke isn't done yet. Enter
trials using MCTs against Alzheimer's
disease. Yes, that's right. There are
clinical trials using MCTs against
Alzheimer's disease. I bet you didn't
expect to be discussing mediumchain
triglycerides in a video about NAD, eh?
Well, unlike all the NAD supplement
studies, both of these studies show a
reversal of Alzheimer's disease with MCT
supplementation. Take that, Emperor
Palpatine.
Then like the Palpatine voice, the dark
side of Alzheimer's is no more.
Okay, let me calm things down a bit.
Yes, both studies showed improvements in
people heading towards Alzheimer's
disease, and yes, it was actually across
multiple cognitive measurements, but the
effect is still quite mild. Could this
be because of the trial length? For
sure. We can't expect to see an
immediate elimination of Alzheimer's. I
also think in general that it's a tall
order for a single molecule to have a
Alzheimer's evisceration effect. If you
are interested in giving it a shot, the
effective dose started at 10 g of MCT up
to 30 g. And if you're looking for more
details on different forms and more
reputable sources and what to focus on,
then check out my master supplement
guide. It includes the MCTs and many
other supplements included with my
insider subscription and updated
regularly. Of course, if the mechanism
is ketosis, which is elevated with MCT
consumption, it might mean that
something like ketogenic diets could
also be an avenue. The answer is
possibly. Unfortunately, what studies
exist are short and tend to be
feasibility trials, which means that
they aren't really designed for
cognitive outcomes in mind. Honestly,
there's more that I could say on the
topic, and I plan on revisiting this in
the future with a special emphasis on
this ketosis angle, but until then, this
is a fascinating initial NAD study. I'm
still down on the NAD supplements, and
we have early clinical evidence that
Alzheimer's can be combed with the help
of MCTs, which I think is a fun
surprise. Now, typically I'd put the
Star Wars theme here because it's only
fitting, but I'll get demonetized. So,
here's the next best thing right after I
point you to the next video on NAD or
this much more promising one on
Alzheimer's disease right here. Thanks
for watching.